Guide to the Jerome J. Shestack papers, 1944-2011 and undated, bulk 1965-2000 RL.11610
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Organizations, 1961-2008 and undated; Approximately 28 large boxes.
  - International Bar Association, 1984-2002 and undated
    - Meeting Minutes and Reports, 1986; 1989 June 9; 2 folders (Box 35)
    - Address List, undated (Box 81)
    - Administrative Files, 1984-1990, undated; 4 folders (Box 35)
      Lists, programs, and memorandums kept by Shestack that document the administrative activities of the International Bar Association. Also contains some correspondence.
    - Administrative Files, 1988-2002, undated; 2 folders (Box 81)
  - International Criminal Court, 1997-2000 and undated
    Materials in this subseries documents a few events and administrative work pertinent to the International Criminal Court, which Shestack played a role in creating during his time as President of the ABA. Related materials may be found in the American Bar Association series or in the International League of Human Rights subseries.
    - International Court of Arbitration Lunch, 1999 (Box 35)
    - NGO Coalition for International Criminal Court, 1998 June (Box 35)
    - Administrative Files, 1997-2000, undated; 2 folders (Box 35)
      Correspondence, reports and publications regarding various International Criminal Court activities
  - International Commission of Jurists, 1973-2008 and undated
    This subseries contains materials documenting Shestack's time as a Commissioner on the International Commission of Jurists, a human rights non-governmental organization based in Geneva, Switzerland. Materials include correspondence between Shestack and ICJ colleagues, speeches by Shestack regarding ICJ, newsletters, reports, memoranda, and administrative files that were previously unfiled.
    - Correspondence, 1980,1983-1984, undated (Box 35)
    - Consultative Activity Reviews, 1998-1999 (Box 35)
    - Speech Material, 1994-1998 (Box 35)
    - Quarterly Report Newsletters, 1980-1989 (Box 81)
    - Other publications, 1973, 1977-1980, 1993 - 1997 (Box 81)
      Includes Report on Activities, The Review Journal, and ICJ newsletters
    - Administrative Files, 1983-1984, 1994-2004, undated; 5 folders (Box 35)
      Maps, report outlines, some correspondence, memos relating to Shestack's work within the International Commission of Jurists
    - Administrative Files, 1999-2008, undated; 10 folders (Box 36)
    - Administrative Files, 2006-2008 (Box 81)
  - Lawyers' Committee for Civil Rights Under Law, 1961-1987, 1993 and undated
    Materials in this subseries include correspondence, subject files, and press releases concerning Shestack's work in the Lawyer's Committee for Civil Rights Under Law, an organization created at the request of President John F. Kennedy. Shestack was a member of the organization's first Board of Trustees.
    - Chronological Correspondence, 1963-1965; 7 folders (Box 36)
      Correspondence regarding the Civil Rights Movement and the activities of the Lawyer's Committee for Civil Rights. Some correspondence is between Shestack and colleagues, but a great deal of correspondence is between Bernard Segal, civil rights lawyer and president of the ABA in the late 1960s.
    - Chronological Correspondence, 1965-1971; 14 folders (Box 37)
    - Alphabetical Correspondence A-I, 1963-1964; 3 folders (Box 37)
    - Civil Rights Correspondence, 1966 (Box 37)
    - David Stahl Correspondence, 1963-1964 (Box 37)
    - American Judicial Conference Correspondence, 1966 (Box 37)
    - Baldwin-Miller Correspondence, 1963 (Box 37)
    - Humphrey and Kuchel Opinion, 1964 (Box 38)
    - Judge Cox, 1964 (Box 38)
    - Kennedy Fundraising Dinner Donations, 1965 (Box 38)
    - Donor Funding, 1965-1966 (Box 38)
    - Community Relations Service, 1964-1966 (Box 38)
    - Airlie Conference, 1965 (Box 38)
    - Statement of Purpose and Activities and other publications, 1965-1969, undated (Box 38)
      Includes publications such as Black Economic Development, Racial Tensions in New York State, and A Nation is Never Finished
    - Speech Locations, undated (Box 38)
    - Speech Requests, 1965 March (Box 38)
    - New Orleans Meeting of Bar Presidents, 1965 (Box 38)
    - Yugoslavia Testimonies, 1993 January (Box 38)
    - Police-Community Relations, 1966-1968 (Box 38)
    - Katzenbach Dinner, 1966 May 4 (Box 38)
    - Organization Inception Files, 1964-1965,1968, 1987, undated (Box 38)
    - Liaisons with Other Groups, 1963-1966, undated; 4 folders (Box 38)
      Correspondence and memorandums between the Lawyer's Committee for Civil Rights and other related organizations
    - NAACP, 1965, undated (Box 38)
    - Washington, DC Conference, 1965 (Box 38)
    - Edward L. Wright, 1963, 1964, 1970 (Box 38)
    - Claude Weaver and Charles Morgan, 1963-1964 (Box 38)
    - Meditation and Consolation Committee, 1963 (Box 38)
    - Binder Files, 1965 (Box 38)
    - Youth Opportunity Campaign, 1965 (Box 38)
    - White House Liaison, 1961-1965; 2 folders (Box 38)
    - Liaison with the Senate, 1964 (Box 39)
    - Washington Supervision Committee, 1969 (Box 39)
    - Press Drafts, 1963 (Box 39)
    - Published Press, 1963; 2 folders (Box 39)
    - Bulletin Published by Anti-Defamation League of B'nai B'rith, 1965 (Box 39)
    - Capital Punishment Project, 1965, undated (Box 39)
    - Civil Rights Movement Files, 1963-1965, 1968-1969, undated; 3 folders (Box 39)
    - Civil Rights Acts, 1964-1966 (Box 39)
    - Civil Rights Agenda for New Orleans, 1965; 2 folders (Box 39)
    - Civil Rights and Disobedience to Law Brochure, 1964 (Box 39)
    - Alabama-Selma, 1965 (Box 39)
    - State Bar Association Support, 1965; 4 folders (Box 39)
    - New Jersey Civil Rights Papers, 1964-1965 (Box 39)
    - State Files, 1964-1965; 2 folders (Box 39)
      Correspondence and reports discussing the State Bar Associations and their involvement with the Civil Rights Movement.
    - Philadelphia Steering Committee Minutes, 1969-1972 (Box 40)
    - Philadelphia Correspondence, 1969-1972; 3 folders (Box 40)
      Correspondence regarding local Philadelphia cases and Philadelphia Bar Association activities held in conjunction with the Lawyer's Committee for Civil Rights
    - Mississippi Project, 1965; 4 folders (Box 40)
      Correspondence and reports regarding the Lawyer's Committee for Civil Rights summer project to bring lawyers to Mississippi in cooperation with the Legal Defense Fund.
    - Mississippi, 1963-1969; 4 folders (Box 40)
      Files concerning the Mississippi Project as well as other Civil Rights Movement activities.
    - Clarksdale, Mississippi, 1963 (Box 40)
    - Mississippi Library, 1965 (Box 40)
    - Mississippi Meetings, 1964 (Box 40)
    - Mississippi Legal Memos, 1965; 2 folders (Box 40)
    - Mississippi Bar Correspondence, 1964-1967; 5 folders (Box 40)
    - Shestack's Personal Source File, 1965, 1969-1971, undated (Box 41)
      File used by Shestack for personal research related to the Lawyer's Committee for Civil Rights
    - Source Material, 1963-1970, undated; 11 folders (Box 41)
      Files regarding the Civil Rights Movement collected by Shestack for use in the context of Lawyer's Committee for Civil Rights Under Law activity. Includes newspaper clippings, reports, and external publications.
    - Civil rights newspaper and magazine clippings, 1963-1966; 6 folders (Box 41)
    - Case files, 1969-1970, undated; 2 folders (Box 41)
      Civil rights cases collected by Lawyer's Committee for Civil Rights.
    - Case files, 1969-1970, undated; 3 folders (Box 42)
    - Current lawsuits, 1965 (Box 42)
    - Transcript and letters for civil rights video, 1988; 2 folders (Box 42)
    - Finance Committee, 1965 (Box 42)
    - Financial Reports, 1964-1966; 2 folders (Box 42)
    - Expenditures, 1964-1967; 4 folders (Box 42)
    - Executive Committee, 1964-1968; 4 folders (Box 42)
      Correspondence, reports concerning the Executive Committee of Lawyers Committee of Civil Rights Under Law
    - Internal Reports, 1964-1968, undated; 4 folders (Box 42)
      Reports circulated within the organization
    - Annual and Anniversary Reports, 1978, 1985-1988, 1993; 2 folders (Box 43)
    - Bylaw Publications, 1959-1965 (Box 43)
    - Meeting Memorandum, 1963 Nov. 12 (Box 43)
    - Annual Meeting report, 1964 (Box 43)
    - Board of Directors, 1965-1968 (Box 43)
    - Board Meeting Minutes, 1965 August (Box 43)
    - General Meeting Memorandums and Minutes, 1970-1972; 4 folders (Box 43)
    - Membership files, 1963-1964; 2 folders (Box 43)
    - General Administrative Files, 1963, 1965-1966, 1978-1990, 1994, undated; 12 folders (Box 43)
      Correspondence, reports, and memorandums concerning the administration of Lawyer's Committee of Civil Rights Under Law. Documents within files are in original arrangement.
    - General Administrative Files, 1963-1999; 2 folders (Box 82)
  - Lawyer's Committee for Human Rights, 1963-1997 and undated
    This subseries documents Shestack's time as a member of the Lawyer's Committee for Human Rights, a non-governmental organization that focuses on legal representation for human rights causes. It was founded in 1975 as the Lawyer's Committee for International Human Rights. It has ties to both the American Bar Association and the International League for Human Rights. Materials include correspondence, subject files, newsletters, membership files, and administrative records.
    - Amnesty Cases, undated (Box 44)
    - State Contact Binder, 1963, undated; 2 folders (Box 44)
      Contains contact addresses and some correspondence
    - Philippines, Uganda, and Chile, 1980-1981 (Box 44)
    - Publications by the Lawyer's Committee for Human Rights, 1978, 1983, 1993 (Box 44)
    - Publications by the Lawyer's Committee for Human Rights, 1988, 1990 (Box 85)
      Includes Vigilantes in the Philippines: A Threat to Democratic Rule and In Defense of Rights: Attacks on Lawyers and Judges in 1990
    - Lawyer to Lawyer Network Newsletter, 1996 Oct. (Box 44)
    - News briefs Newsletter, 1989 (Box 44)
    - Law and Human Rights Research Sources, 1983-1991, undated; 6 folders (Box 44)
      Original and photocopy versions of publications, reports, and essays not produced by the Lawyer's Committee for Human Rights but pertaining to human rights and related subjects.
    - Board Meeting Minutes, 1978 Oct. 5, 1978 Dec.; 2 folders (Box 44)
    - Membership Records, 1963; 7 folders (Box 44)
    - Administrative Correspondence, 1980-1982 (Box 44)
    - Administrative Files, 1975-1997, undated; 8 folders (Box 45)
      Correspondence, newsletters, and reports related to the Lawyer's Committee for Human Rights Activities. Original arrangement within folders.
    - Administrative Files, 1964, 1978-1990; 3 folders (Box 82)
  - United Nations Commission on Human Rights, 1969-2001 and undated
    Materials document Shestack's activities as U.S. ambassador to the United Nations Commission on Human Rights, a functional commission of the U.N. that focused on human rights situations in various countries. Shestack was appointed by President Jimmy Carter in 1979. Materials include correspondence between Shestack and others regarding the U.N. Commission, conference proceedings, Commission agendas, meeting minutes, subject files, and administrative files.
    Related materials can be found in the Events subseries of the Subjects series.
    - Correspondence, 1970-1982; 9 folders (Box 45)
    - General Assembly, 1980 (Box 46)
    - International League for Human Rights involvement in UN Commission activities, 1984 (Box 46)
    - 36 Session Report Addendum, 1980 (Box 46)
    - Human Rights Internet Reporter, 1984, undated (Box 46)
    - Telegram Tables, 1980-1981, undated (Box 46)
    - Telegrams, 1980 (Box 82)
    - Articles, 1977 (Box 46)
    - High Commissioner, 1979-1980 (Box 46)
    - Confidential Internal Announcements, 1980 (Box 46)
    - Meeting of the UN Commission on Human Rights, 36th session, 1979 Dec. 24 (Box 46)
    - UN Conference on Human Rights, 2001 (Box 46)
    - UN Human Rights Conference Proceedings, 2001 Feb. 1; 2 folders (Box 46)
    - State Department Reports, undated (Box 46)
    - Subcommission, 1984 Aug. 1 (Box 46)
    - Afghanistan, 1976-1980 (Box 82)
    - Argentina, 1980 (Box 46)
    - Madrid Conference, 1980 (Box 46)
    - Poland, 1980 (Box 46)
    - Research, 1980 (Box 46)
    - Session Agenda Items, 1978-1980; 9 folders (Box 46)
      Organization Meeting agendas
    - Session Agenda Items, 1969-1971,1980; 4 folders (Box 47)
    - Session Agenda Items, 1991-1992 (Box 82)
    - Administrative Files, 1971, 1977-1989, undated; 17 folders (Box 47)
      UN Commission session files, memorandums, and reports regarding the activities of the group.
    - Administrative Files, 1979-1989; 10 folders (Box 82)
  - American Jewish Committee, 1969-1999 and undated
    Materials document Shestack's work as a member of the American Jewish Committee, a Jewish advocacy organization, for which he served on the Board of Directors. Materials include correspondence between Shestack and his colleagues regarding the committee; meeting minutes; administrative files; and materials on the Blaustein institute of Jewish Human Rights, a section of the American Jewish Committee that focuses on international human rights. Shestack was an Institute chair and prominent member of its steering committee.
    - Correspondence, 1972 Jan. - 1973 Dec. (Box 48)
    - Correspondence, 1974 Jan. (Box 48)
    - Correspondence, 1978 (Box 83)
    - Blaustein Institute, 1984-1982 and undated; 9 folders (Box 83)
      Correspondence, reports, and administrative files from the American Jewish Committee's Jacob Blaustein Institute for the Advancement of Human Rights
    - Minutes, 1970-1975 (Box 48)
    - Administrative Files, 1969-1975, undated; 6 folders (Box 48)
      Reports, correspondence, and publications regarding the activities of the American Jewish Committee International
    - Administrative Files, 1972-1999, undated (Box 83)
  - Luso-American Business Council, 1985-1989 and undated
    Shestack's work on the Luso-American Business Council, a non-profit organization founded by American Portuguese and based in New York City, is documented here. Materials include correspondence between Shestack and others pertaining to the Council, organizational tax information, and administrative files.
    - Correspondence, 1985-1987 (Box 48)
    - Tax Information, 1985 (Box 48)
    - Administrative Files, 1986-1989, undated; 5 folders (Box 48)
      Reports, correspondence, and publications regarding the activities of the Luso-American Business Council.
  - Other Organizations, 1961-1997 and undated
    Subseries comprises files from a few other human rights organizations and legal groups in which Shestack was active throughout his career. Materials include memos, some correspondence, publications, and administrative files from each of the groups.
    - Commission on Security and Cooperation in Europe, 1980, 1984, 1991, undated; 8 folders (Box 49)
      Reports, printed articles, some correspondence
    - Commission on Security and Cooperation in Europe, 1980, 1982; 2 folders (Box 83)
    - American Arbitration Association Certificates and Memos, 1961, 1966, undated (Box 49)
    - Carter-Menil Human Rights Foundation, 1987-1991, undated; 2 folders (Box 49)
    - Human Rights Watch, 1982-1986 (Box 83)
    - US Commission on Improving the Effectiveness of the UN, 1991-1993 (Box 83)
    - US Commission on Improving the Effectiveness of the UN, 1992-1997; 12 folders (Box 84)
      Some correspondence, reports, and administrative files from the US Commission on Improving the Effectiveness of the UN
- Correspondence, 1945-2000 and undated; Approximately 2 large boxes.
  Series files contain correspondence between Shestack, his colleagues, human rights activists, and noted politicians, throughout his career. The majority of the correspondence is professional in nature. Some correspondence is from Shestack on behalf of an organization. The first subseries is arranged chronologically by decade, while the second subseries is arranged alphabetically by subject, including some bound correspondence files that Shestack arranged by correspondent last name. One file contains some correspondence Shestack wrote to Martin Luther King, Jr.
  Related correspondence, sometimes in large amounts, can be found throughout the American Bar Association, Organizations, and the Subject Files series.
  - Chronological, 1945-2000 and undated
    The Chronological Correspondence subseries contains correspondence between Shestack and his colleagues arranged by decade. Most correspondence is of a professional nature and discusses Shestack's activities in law and human rights advocacy.
    - Correspondence, 1945, 1953, 1960-1989; 6 folders (Box 49)
    - Correspondence, 1970-1979 (Box 85)
    - Correspondence, 1980-2000, undated; 9 folders (Box 50)
    - Correspondence, 1980-2000, undated; 2 folders (Box 85)
  - Subject, 1953-1996 and undated
    Subseries consists of correspondence arranged alphabetically by subject title. A few subject files are sets of correspondence bound by Shestack according to correspondent last name. Subject correspondence topics include the United States Holocaust Museum, the Philadelphia Bar Association Sitting Judges, as well as letters from Shestack to Martin Luther King, Jr. during the Civil Rights Movement.
    - Alphabetical Correspondence "A, B", 1957-1975 (Box 50)
    - Afghanistan: Society for Rule of Law (Dhaka) Correspondence, 1990 (Box 50)
    - Alphabetical Correspondence "G", 1957-1973 (Box 50)
    - Holocaust Museum Correspondence, 1996 (Box 50)
    - Mary Hurtig Correspondence, 1991 Jan 7 (Box 50)
    - Correspondence to Martin Luther King, Jr., 1965 (Box 50)
    - Lawyer's Seminar on Mid-East Issues Correspondence, 1972 Jan (Box 50)
    - Alphabetical Correspondence, "N, O", 1954-1970 (Box 50)
    - Philadelphia Bar Association Sitting Judges Correspondence, 1971 (Box 50)
    - Alphabetical Correspondence "P, Q", 1953-1977 (Box 50)
    - Stamp Correspondence, 1965-1968 (Box 50)
- Subject Files, 1951-2011 and undated; Approximately 19 large boxes.
  Series contains large series of subject files arranged in five subseries, assembled by Jerome Shestack over the course of his career. The majority of the files relates to Shestack's professional work concerning the intersection of law and human rights, but a few personal subject files are also included. Files contain mostly correspondence, reports, and memoranda. There are a few recordings on audiocassette and video.
  The series is arranged into these subseries: People, Countries, Events and Groups, Personal Binder Files, and Other Materials. Highlights of the series include subject files on President Jimmy Carter, George Bush, René Cassin, Bernard Segal, and many others; and materials on a series of 1970s seminars for lawyers in Israel. Personal files include biographical materials on Shestack's career; research on Eleanor Roosevelt and other topics, photographs, and awards and certificates. The last series contains a group of unfiled materials that were left intact.
  Original media are closed to use. Listening and viewing copies must be made for access. Please contact the Rubenstein Library staff before coming to use this collection.
  - People, 1955-2003 and undated
    Materials in this subseries document Shestack's connections to many people, including many important political leaders and professional colleagues. Files contain correspondence between Shestack and his colleagues as well as reports and memoranda associated with specific people. Highlights of the subseries include files regarding President George Bush, President Jimmy Carter, Barry Goldwater, Estes Kefauver, and Bernard Segal. Files are arranged in alphabetical order by last name.
    - Yosef Begun, 1984 (Box 51)
    - William Brennan, Jr. Human Rights Award, 1968-1994 (Box 84)
    - George Bush, 1971-1973, 1988 (Box 51)
    - Vincent A. Carroll, 1961, 1962, 1966 (Box 51)
    - Jimmy Carter - White House, 1979-1980, undated; 2 folders (Box 51)
      White House correspondence from President Jimmy Carter
    - Bob Casey, 1970-1973, 1985-1987 (Box 51)
    - René Cassin, 1971 (Box 51)
    - Senator Joseph Clark, 1968 (Box 51)
    - Roberta Cohen, 1989 (Box 51)
    - William S. Cohen, 1984 (Box 51)
    - Coughlin for Congress, 1984 (Box 51)
    - Lynn Cutler, 1982 (Box 51)
    - Richardson Dilsworth, 1965 (Box 51)
    - Yoram Dinstein, 1976-1988 (Box 84)
    - Michael Dukakis, 1988-1989; 3 folders (Box 51)
      correspondence and reports for dukakis campaign
    - John Easton for Governor, 1984 (Box 51)
    - Bob Edgar for Congress, 1983-1988 (Box 51)
    - Bob Edgar and Peter Kostmayer, 1978, 1987, undated (Box 51)
    - Josh Eilberg, 1965-1966 (Box 51)
    - Allen Ertel, 1984 (Box 51)
    - Dante Fascell, 1982 (Box 51)
    - Tom Foglietta, 1982-1988 (Box 51)
    - Wyche Fowler, 1985-1986 (Box 51)
    - Don Fraser, 1978-1985 (Box 51)
    - Sam Gejdenson, 1982-1985 (Box 51)
    - Richard Gephardt, 1989 (Box 51)
    - Jim Gillin, 1984 (Box 51)
    - Wilson Goode, 1983 (Box 51)
    - Bill Gray, 1982, 1988, undated (Box 51)
    - Bill Green, 1976-1980, undated; 2 folders (Box 51)
    - Barry Goldwater, 1952, 1964, undated; 2 folders (Box 51)
    - Marilyn Haft, 1981 (Box 51)
    - Gary Hart, 1985-1987 (Box 51)
    - Gerry Helman, 1980-1984 (Box 51)
    - A. Leon Higginbotham, 1987 (Box 51)
    - H. H. Humphrey, 1968, undated (Box 51)
    - H. H. Humphrey, 1968-1972, undated; 3 folders (Box 52)
    - Jim Hunt, 1984 (Box 52)
    - Judge Leonard A. Ivanoski, 1989 (Box 52)
    - Henry Jackson, 1976 (Box 52)
    - Senator Estes Kefauver, 1955-1963 (Box 52)
    - John Kerry, 2002-2003 (Box 52)
    - Richard Lillich, 1985 (Box 52)
    - Netanel Lorch, 1973 (Box 52)
    - Theodor Meron, 1981, 1985, 1989, undated (Box 52)
    - Bernard Segal, 1963-1989, undated; 4 folders (Box 52)
      Correspondence between Shestack and Segal and speeches by Segal.
    - Bernard Segal, 1973-1982, undated; 2 folders (Box 84)
    - Marciarose Shestack, 1975, 1989 (Box 84)
      Columns written by Marciarose Shestack, Jerome Shestack's wife
  - Countries, 1951-2008 and undated
    Materials in this subseries concern Shestack's interest and involvement with human rights and legal issues in different countries. The most substantial file groups pertain to: Argentina; China; Israel; Russia (and Soviet Union); and South Africa.
    Some files contain reports and other documents concerning human rights in connection to various human rights and legal organizations of which Shestack was a member. Others contain testimony and trial information related to specific human rights violations and abuses. Subseries is arranged in alphabetical order by country.
    Some related materials may be found in various sections of the Organizations series.
    - Africa, 1981, undated (Box 52)
    - Argentina, 1979, 1983-1984, undated (Box 52)
    - Bolivia, 1980 Dec. 4 (Box 52)
    - Bosnia Trip, 1991-1993 (Box 52)
    - Cambodia, 1987 (Box 52)
    - Canada, 1981 (Box 52)
    - Chile, 1982-1986; 2 folders (Box 84)
    - China, 1996-2000; 4 folders (Box 52)
      Reports and correspondence regarding human rights in China
    - China, 1999-2000, undated (Box 53)
    - Costa Rica, undated (Box 53)
    - Cuba, 1986-1987 (Box 53)
    - East Timor, 1981 October 19 (Box 53)
    - Egypt, 1984, 1987, undated (Box 53)
    - El Salvador, 1988 (Box 53)
    - East Germany, 1984 July 17 (Box 53)
    - Geneva, Switzerland, 1984 (Box 53)
    - Guatemala, 1983-1984 (Box 53)
    - Guinea, 1984, undated (Box 53)
    - Haiti, 1984 (Box 53)
    - Helsinki, Finland, 1979-1981, 1983-1989, undated; 3 folders (Box 53)